<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A briefe consideration of mans iniquitie, and Gods iustice wherein the distinction of 1. sinnes into veniall, mortall, 2. sinnes and punishments into æquall, vnæquall is scholastically examined.</title>
            <author>Higgons, Theophilus, 1578?-1659.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1608</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 38 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03333</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13453</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S116034</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99851251</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99851251</idno>
            <idno type="VID">16521</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A03333)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 16521)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1106:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A briefe consideration of mans iniquitie, and Gods iustice wherein the distinction of 1. sinnes into veniall, mortall, 2. sinnes and punishments into æquall, vnæquall is scholastically examined.</title>
                  <author>Higgons, Theophilus, 1578?-1659.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 32, [6] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[By R. Bradock], for Roger Iackson, and are to be sold at his shop in Fleetstreet, neere the Conduit,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1608.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"To the reader" signed: Theophilus Hyggons.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: Of mans iniquity, and Gods iustice.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Redemption --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:16521:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A BRIEFE CONSIDERATION <hi>Of Mans Iniquitie, and</hi> Gods Iuſtice: Wherein the diſtinction of
<list>
                  <item>1. Sinnes into
<list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>
                              <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>eniall,</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Mortall,</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. Sinnes and Puniſhments into
<list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Aequall,</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>
                              <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nequall</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list> 
               <hi>Is Scholaſticallie Examined.</hi>
            </p>
            <q xml:lang="lat">
               <p>Miſerere mei Domine indigna faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entis, &amp; digna patientis.</p>
               <bibl>S. <hi>Aug.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Imprinted at London, for <hi>Roger Iackson,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop in Fleetſtreet, neere the Conduit. 1608.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="author_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:16521:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16521:2"/>
            <head>¶ The Authour to the <hi>Pretended Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE <hi>CHVRCH</hi> (in the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall ſignificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the word) is a Body vnited togither, in all the partes ioyned with the Head by a myſticall vnion. And the <hi>Old Enemie</hi> hath diuerſlie aſſaulted both Head and Bodie, with vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placable malice, but limited po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer.</p>
            <p>Yet ſtill hee attempteth ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, and as he is a ſpirituall E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemie, ſo are his weapons ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:16521:3"/>
            <p>Sometimes he prouoketh vs to ſinne in <hi>Morall</hi> things, as in ſins of <hi>action, Contra bonum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sometimes in things <hi>Intellectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all,</hi> as in ſins of <hi>Opinion Contra ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The latter is of two ſorts: either <hi>haereticall</hi> againſt the Head: Or <hi>ſchiſmaticall</hi> againſt the Body.</p>
            <p>The Hereſies againſt the Head, are eyther againſt his Natures or Perſons, or Offices.</p>
            <p>The two former were olde he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies, and long ſince condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</p>
            <p>The latter, are diuers hereſies ſprung vp as tares amongſt good wheat in ſucceding ages.</p>
            <p>Such are diuers of your opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, &amp; namely againſt the Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood of Chriſt conſiſting in <hi>Satiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction</hi> and <hi>Interceſſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The former you haue ſundry waies violated, and not a little by
<pb facs="tcp:16521:3"/> your miſapplyed diſtinction of <hi>Veniall</hi> and <hi>Mortall</hi> ſinnes: which I haue a little rectified in this briefe Declaration, and alſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mooued that imputation of the <hi>Aequality</hi> of ſinne and puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which you ſay, muſt neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily enſue, if your conceipt ſhould vaniſh.</p>
            <p>If you make no anſwere hereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, you either want Charitie to free me from errour, or ability to diſcharge your ſelues from ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereof. And if you make any aunſwer, let your lynes be more full of ſubſtance to ſatiſfie the point, then of malice to diſgrace the Author: who entirely wiſhing your ſaluation in Chriſts Iuſtice, commendeth you to Gods mercy in him.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Fare ye well,</salute>
               <dateline>
                  <date>14. Octo. 1607.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:16521:4"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:16521:4"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A</hi> Briefe Conſideration, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>ENIALL</hi> ſins are rather <hi>prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter legem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Papists opinion briefly reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</note> then <hi>Contra legem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Veniall</hi> &amp; <hi>mortall</hi> are ſo to bee e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed from their owne nature: For <hi>veniall</hi> condignely deſerue onely temporall puniſhmentes, and <hi>mortall</hi> deſerue a ternall puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhments, and both theſe in diuine iuſtice. And hence is the <hi>inaequality</hi> of ſinne moſt properly, and prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:16521:5"/> conceiued. In which reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect there are certaine temporary puniſhments alſo in Purgatorie, remaining for thoſe, whoſe ſinnes in this life are not ſufficiently pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, and for which they haue not worthily ſatiſfied.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion recited and decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</note>ALL ſins <hi>ex natura ſua &amp; merito</hi> are <hi>mortall,</hi> deſeruing condign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in diuine Iuſtice, eternall death.</p>
            <p>Theſe ſinnes are alſo <hi>veniall,</hi> not <hi>propriè,</hi> but <hi>impropriè &amp; ex euentu</hi> onely. They are <hi>veniall</hi> by grace according to the quality and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of our Repentance, by which we are capable of pardon. <hi>Quod verum eſt in adultis,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>But to ſay <hi>Peccatum</hi> and yet <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niale</hi> ſimply, and not <hi>Mortale</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perlie, it is a virtuall Contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. For they are in that ſenſe, <hi>termini incompoſſibiles,</hi> and can con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt together, no more then fire
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:16521:5"/> and cold, water and dry, or the like; the accident being ſuch as is repugnant to the proper, or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall quality of the ſubiect. For there is no compoſition of merely oppoſites, nor conſtruction of mutually deſtructiues.</p>
            <p>And if any man aſke, 1. how <hi>peccatum</hi> can be a ſubiect, it ſelfe being in nature nothing, or 2. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing but an accident, how can it be the ſubiect of an accident?</p>
            <p>We anſwere,</p>
            <p>To the firſt: that though nothing hath Being, which is not from God, and ſo ſinne is nothing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is not from God, yet the forme of it, being an obliquity in the ſubſtance, or quality, or action of a reaſonable creature, taking integrity from the ſame, ſo farre as it proceedeth: Sinne hath <hi>eſſe priuatinum,</hi> in that which hath <hi>eſſe poſitinum</hi> from God. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:16521:6"/> 
               <hi>Subiectum mali est bonum, quia malum ſubſistit in ente, quod in ſebo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num eſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To the ſecond, that though <hi>mortale in peccato</hi> haue not ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per an inherency, as ordinary Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents haue in their ſubiects, yet it is ſo naturally in it, that it is in nature inſeparable from it: but <hi>vltimum et independens ſubiectum, eſt homo peccans, vel Angelus pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cans.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherefore the diſtinction of ſinnes into <hi>Veniall</hi> and <hi>Mortall,</hi> ariſeth not <hi>ex ipſis Rebus,</hi> but <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonis:</hi> and hence it followeth, <gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>t all ſinnes are damnable <hi>in</hi> all me<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, not <hi>to</hi> all men; all deſeruing, <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> not all receyuing damnation. <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to the Reprobate, no ſinne is final<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>veniall,</hi> and to the Elect, no ſinne is finally <hi>mortall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Notwithſtanding it muſt bee obſerued, that one ſinne <hi>ſimpliciter
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:16521:6"/> &amp; vniuerſaliter eſt mortale,</hi> becauſe it is not onely puniſhable, but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uermore puniſhed with eternall death, in all that commit the ſame &amp; this is <hi>Peccatum contra Spiritum Sanctum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For though it be not fully clee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red (at leaſte in the iudgement of many men) what this Sinne is, and wherein the formality of the ſame conſiſteth, yet wee obſerue this difference betwixt this, and other mortall ſinnes (I call ſinnes <hi>Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall</hi> two wayes: firſt by way of <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication,</hi> and ſo to ſay a <hi>mortall</hi> ſin,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mortale,</hi> eſt genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liter nota <hi>explica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiua,</hi> ſpecialiter eſt nota <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctiua.</hi>
               </note> it is to ſhew the nature of all ſins: ſecondly by way of <hi>diſtinction:</hi> and ſo to ſay a <hi>mortall</hi> ſinne, it is to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne this ſinne, whereof I now ſpeake.)</p>
            <p>That <hi>Impenitencie</hi> maketh other remiſſible ſinnes not to be remit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, but doth not perpetually and neceſſarily attend thoſe ſinnes:
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:16521:7"/> Whereas this ſinne is ſimply ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remiſſible, the party ſo ſinning beeing euermore obdurate by his owne vniuſt action, and the iuſt ſubtraction of Gods grace, ſo that Impenitency followeth it <hi>ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitate ineuitabili:</hi> and therefore it is called <hi>mortall</hi> in an eminent de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, and is neuer <hi>veniall:</hi> not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God in his abſolute power, cannot forgiue it, but becauſe in his iuſt will he hath decreed neuer to forgiue it.</p>
            <p>This is it which our Lord ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth of, <hi>Mathew</hi> 12.31. and which his beloued Diſciple vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, ſaying: <hi>There is a ſinne vnto death: and there is a ſinne not vnto death:</hi> diſtinguiſhing not betwixt ſome ſinnes <hi>mortall</hi> in nature, and others <hi>veniall</hi> in nature; but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt one ſinne ſimply <hi>mortall</hi> in nature, and in neceſſary effect vnto all: and all other ſinnes ſimplie
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:16521:7"/> 
               <hi>mortall</hi> in nature, but not in neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary effect vnto all: and therefore poſſibly <hi>veniall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And if any Papiſt ſay, that <hi>Veni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all</hi> Sinnes muſt bee repented of: I aunſwer, that this Repentance be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing omitted, maketh not a <hi>Veniall</hi> Sinne to be a <hi>mortall</hi> ſinne in their iudgement: For then they ſhoulde agree with vs, who ſay that a <hi>mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall</hi> ſinne is <hi>veniall</hi> by repentance, and that a <hi>veniall</hi> ſinne (as all ſins except one, are, <hi>propter poſſi<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ilita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem Poenitentiae</hi>) for want of Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance is finally <hi>mortall.</hi> But the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts ſay, that ſinnes <hi>veniall</hi> not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented of, are not <hi>mortall,</hi> nor me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritoriouſly puniſhable by eternall death. If they ſay not thus, there is no controuerſy betwixt vs: and if they ſay thus, there is no reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation, as far as I can conceiue.</p>
            <p>The Ancients ſpeaking of <hi>mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall</hi> ſinnes, vnderſtand great ſins,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:16521:8"/> 
               <hi>Peccata vaſtantia conſcientiam,</hi> ſuch as vſually exclude grace, by which our ſinnes become veniall vnto vs.</p>
            <p>To returne a little back againe, that wee may proceede forward more orderly, we note that Impae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitency is not <hi>the Sinne</hi> againſt the Holy Ghoſt, becauſe it is in Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganes alſo, who neuer knewe his Diuine Perſon, nor felt his liuelie motion. It is not <hi>formale huius pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cati,</hi> but <hi>conſequens.</hi> In all other ſins it is rather contingent, then con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent. For as no ſinne can bee forgiuen without repentance, ſo this ſinne excludeth poſſibility of repentance, and therefore cannot be forgiuen. <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.4.</p>
            <p>NOW as Death is the wages of all ſinnes, ſo Chriſt onely is the propitiation of all ſins, and both by merite.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:16521:8"/>
            <p>He taketh away <hi>Originall</hi> ſinne: yet Baptiſme is required ordinarily as the inſtrument.</p>
            <p>Hee taketh away <hi>Actuall</hi> ſinne: yet Repentance is required euermore in thoſe that are of Capacity.</p>
            <p>Neither doth hee take away ſome ſort of Sins onely, and not al ſorts. For hee taketh away all <hi>Kinds</hi> of ſins, Actuall aſwell as Originall: all <hi>degrees</hi> of Actuall, the leſſer, as well as the greater, leauing no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing vnſatiſfied, either in the guilt or puniſhment.</p>
            <p>For if hee tooke away ſome kinds of ſinne, <hi>Originall</hi> and not <hi>Actuall:</hi> or ſome degree of actuall, <hi>great</hi> and not <hi>little:</hi> Or if hee tooke away the <hi>guilt,</hi> and not the <hi>puniſhment:</hi> or <hi>part</hi> of the puniſhment (as beeing ſatisfactory) and not <hi>all,</hi> hee were not an whole, but an halfe Redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, which is an impious doctrin: and wee not wholly, but halfe ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:16521:9"/> which is an vncomfortable doctrine.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">He alone trode the winepreſſe, &amp;c.</note>But he hath done all theſe things alone, helping vs, not by meriting grace for vs to helpe our ſelues withall: and ſauing vs, not by gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing vs power to ſaue our ſelues withall: but performing euerie part, and parcell of ſatiſfaction, by actiue obedience, in fulfilling the law, and paſſiue obedience in ſuffering for our tranſgreſſing of the law; that euery part and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of meryt being entirely in his own perſon, he might haue all the glory in ſuch an excellent benefyt of his redeemed brethren. <hi>Thou art worthy O Lord, &amp;c. Apo.</hi> 5.9.</p>
            <p>Therefore as it is true, which S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith: <hi>He that made thee without thy ſelfe, doth not ſaue thee without the ſelfe;</hi> becauſe in <hi>Creation</hi> God required nothing of vs, but in <hi>Saluation</hi> hee requireth ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:16521:9"/> of vs; a ſanctified heart,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>But theſe alſo are his gifts,</hi> Da quod iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bes, &amp; iubo quod uis.</note> a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed will, which muſt be obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to his diuine will: ſo it is true, Hee that made vs without our ſelues, ſaueth vs without our ſelues alſo: becauſe as man did not concurre <hi>operatiuely</hi> with God in <hi>Creation,</hi> ſo he doth not concur <hi>meritoriouſly</hi> with him in <hi>Saluation.</hi> Wherefore though Man muſt do ſomthing toward his ſaluation in the <hi>Court of new obedience,</hi> after his acquittall in the <hi>Court of Iuſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> yet he can doe nothing by way of merit in either; becauſe he hath not power in the ſtate of ſinne, or grace, actiuely or paſſiuely to ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie Gods Iuſtice.</p>
            <p>For though God afflicteth his Children, and though his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren muſt liue conformably to his Lawe; yet the firſt being a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly and gentle correction, it looſeth the property of <hi>Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:16521:10"/> and the ſecond being a filial (but vnperfect) obedience,<note place="margin">Poena.</note> it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not haue the eſtimation of <hi>Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iuſtitia.</note> ſo that neither is ſatiſfacto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie in the Court of the ſupreme Iudge.</p>
            <p>For ſinne is the tranſgreſſion of the law (without the law there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no ſinne) and no ignoraunce herein can totally excuſe the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender, though inuincible igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance may mitigate the degree of his offence. Therefore euery ſinne is committed (mediatly at leaſte) againſt an infinite Obiect, God the Author of the law, who conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently requireth an infinite pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment.</p>
            <p>Wherefore as it was neceſſarie, that our Redeemer ſhould haue our true humane <hi>nature,</hi> that ſinne in it might be puniſhed <hi>Iuſtly:</hi> So this humane nature was to ſubſiſt in an infinite <hi>Perſon,</hi> that ſinne by
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:16521:10"/> it might be conquered <hi>fully.</hi> And hence was the incarnation of our bleſſed Lord,<note place="margin">By power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full aſſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, not by naturall generation.</note> who tooke our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture (ſanctified by the holy Ghoſt) into the vnity of his perſon.</p>
            <p>Such a Redemer we were to haue, conſidering the quality of our ſinne, and Gods Iuſtice: that hee might make <hi>proportionable</hi> ſatiſfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
            <p>But when God is to puniſh a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner according to the proper merit of his vnpardoned ſinne, hauing not meanes to ſatisfie his iuſtice vpon any infiniteneſſe of mans perſon, which he is to puniſh, he chooſeth the infiniteneſſe of time, wherein he will puniſh him, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to make ſome manner of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion betwixt the ſinne of man, and his owne Iuſtice.</p>
            <p>But becauſe the perſon ſinning and puniſhed, is in no manner matchable with the perſon (or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:16521:11"/> nature) offended and puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, therefore this puniſhment may be truely called <hi>Paſſion,</hi> but is not <hi>Satiſfaction:</hi> whereas the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finiteneſſe of our Redeemers per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, made his paſſion to bee a true ſatiſfaction, ſufficient for the ſinne of ten thouſand worlds.</p>
            <p>Hence it followeth, that all our ſufferings in this life, whatſoeuer, are but expurgations of the matter of ſinne, not ſatiſfaction for the guilte thereof, nor may ſtand in place of condigne puniſhment: which are both taken away ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently by Chriſt: the firſt beeing imputed to him, &amp; the ſecond in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted on him in his death, that we might haue the reall benefit there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of effectually by the working po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of the Spirit.</p>
            <p>And therefore no ſinne is ſo <hi>ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall</hi> in its nature, as that any man may worthily ſatiſfie for the ſame
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:16521:11"/> in this life, or in the life to come.</p>
            <div n="2" type="inquiry">
               <head>Secunda Quaestio.</head>
               <p>YET notwithſtanding we ſay, that there is inequality in <hi>Culpa,</hi> and conſequently in <hi>poena</hi> alſo.</p>
               <p>For if the puniſhment were e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall, wee muſt ſuppoſe that all ſins are equall, which is falſe: or that God is not iuſt, which is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious; or that he doth not puniſh a greater ſinne, more then a leſſer, becauſe he is mercifull, which is a ſenſeleſſe opinion, obſcuring the cleare diſtinction of his Iuſtice. Only, to make his Iuſtice and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy conſiſt together in puniſhing the very Diuells, &amp; other damned miſcreants, we ſay, that he puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth them not ſo much as their ſins haue deſerued. Which if it ſeeme an hard ſaying, it is to thoſe that know not how to value the ſin of man, and the Iuſtice of God.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:16521:12"/>1. Firſt concerning the <hi>Inaequa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of ſinne,</hi> wee ſay that it may be conſidered principally in three things.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <note place="margin">Diuerſitas Obiecti in quod pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>camus.</note>1. In reſpect of the <hi>Obiect</hi> againſt which we ſinne: ſo a ſinne againſt God, is greater then a ſin againſt man: a ſinne againſt the firſt Table then the ſecond. But this muſt be truely conceiued.</p>
               <p>For if wee compare a ſinne in the leaſt part of a commandement of the firſt Table, with a ſinne in the greateſt part of a commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the ſecond Table, the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſinne is more haynous then the former. For though <hi>Charitas primò ordinatur in Deum,</hi> and euery breach of the law be a breache of charity,<note place="margin">Peccamus in Deum immediatè in quibuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam pecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu &amp; me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatè in alijs.</note> yet ſome compariſon is to bee obſerued, as well in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of the act, as in the order of the act.</p>
               <p>Though in the order of the act,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:16521:12"/> charity bee more broken in the leaſt ſinne againſt God, then in the greateſt againſt man, yet in the degree and quality of the act, it is more broken in the greateſt ſinne againſt man immediately, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the leaſt ſinne againſt God immediatly. Which is manifeſt, becauſe the Sabbath was made diſpenſable <hi>propter opera neceſſitatis &amp; charitatis,</hi> as it appeareth by Chriſt, the interpreter of the law, who was the giuer thereof.</p>
               <p>Yet if the ſame lawgiuer did not forbid the greateſt ſinne againſt man, who forbiddeth the leaſt ſin againſt himſelfe, this rule could not hold.</p>
               <p>But if we compare a ſinne againſt the firſt Table, with a ſin againſt the ſecond in <hi>aquall</hi> &amp; <hi>parallell acts,</hi> the firſt is ſimply the greater ſin.</p>
               <p>Likewiſe, as generally a ſinne againſt God, is greater then a ſinne
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:16521:13"/> againſt ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for the <hi>eſſentiall diuerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> of the Obiect; ſo a ſinne againſt one man, may bee greater then a ſinne againſt an other, for the <hi>acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentall diuerſitie</hi> of the obiect: As in the eminency of place againſt a <hi>King:</hi> in the propinquity of bloud againſt a <hi>Parent, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For though all men <hi>naturallie</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered are the ſame, yet <hi>ciuilly,</hi> and <hi>morally,</hi> they are not. And therfore the degree of ſinne is much varied for theſe reſpects.</p>
               <p n="2">2. In reſpect of the <hi>matter</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we ſinne:<note place="margin">Diuerſitas materiae circa qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> peccamus, vel quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titatis e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſdem materiae.</note> ſo murder is a greater ſin then theft, becauſe life is more pretious then goods.</p>
               <p>Likewiſe if we compare ſinnes in the ſame kind or matter, one may be greater then another, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the extent, or quantita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue meaſure. As to kill three men it is a greater ſin then to kill two: to ſteale 100 pound, then 10: if no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:16521:13"/> els be interuenient. For great diuerſity of ſinne, ariſeth out of the variety of circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</p>
               <p n="3">3. In reſpect of the <hi>manner</hi> how we offend: ſo a ſinne of malice,<note place="margin">Diuerſitas modi quo peccamus.</note> is greater then a ſinne of infirmitie, a ſinne of ignorance, then a ſin of negligence.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Th. Aquin. in quae. de ordine praecept: Decalogi,</hi> obſerueth, that the laſt commandements are well diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed, <hi>Propter peccatum operis,</hi> in the commandement <hi>Non furtum facies. Propter peccatum Oris,</hi> in the commandement <hi>Non loquêris fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum &amp;c. Propter peccatum Cordis,</hi> in the commandement <hi>Non concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſces.</hi> But he diſtinguiſheth the laſt into two, without good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gruity. For to couet an other mans wiſe, and to couet another mans Oxe, is the ſame <hi>manner</hi> of coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, but the <hi>matter</hi> is not the ſame
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:16521:14"/> which maketh not this to be two commandements: For the <hi>manner</hi> of coueting, which is <hi>concupiſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia ſine conſenſu,</hi> being but one, and the <hi>matter</hi> coveted be diuers, the commandement is one, and not diuers: But the ſame things being forbidden in the ſeauenth &amp; eighth commandements to be coueted <hi>cum conſenſu,</hi> there the commandements are diuers, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are broken principally in <hi>Opere,</hi> not in <hi>Corde</hi> only. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as this laſt is broken not in <hi>Opere,</hi> but only in <hi>Corde</hi> without full con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to the tentation.</p>
               <p>And whereas ſome ſins conſiſt onely in <hi>immanent</hi> action being fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed in the mind, either proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly or fully, as <hi>pride,</hi> or vnproperly and caſually as <hi>murther</hi> (for pride is abſolutely complete in the mind, but murther is not) &amp; ſome in <hi>tranſient</hi> action, beeing accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:16521:14"/> by the body; the laſt is greater then the firſt, becauſe there is a farther addition in it the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the firſt. The luſting after a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man is <hi>mentall</hi> adultery, though it proceed no farther, which is for want of meanes only. For <hi>Adulter animo, non niſi inuito castus est cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A ſinne in mynd is more eaſily committed then a ſin in the body, becauſe it findeth leſſe impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: and a ſinne in the order of it, is committed firſt in the minde, and ſecondly by the body, as it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth in the firſt ſin of our firſt Parents. Euery farther additio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the ſinne more intenſe in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree.</p>
               <p>Now ſince there is ſuch <hi>ina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quality</hi> in <hi>Culpa,</hi> there is alſo ine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quality in <hi>Poena,</hi> becauſe the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Gods Iuſtice, whence it proceedeth, hath a relatiue reſpect
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:16521:15"/> to our ſin, which, in what kind ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer it be, is meritoriouſly puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhable by eternall death.</p>
               <p>The puniſhment is double, <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uatiue</hi> and <hi>Poſitiue.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">
                  <hi>1.</hi> The <hi>Priuatiue</hi> payne (called <hi>Poena Damni</hi>) is the want of deſira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble good. Such is the excluſion out of heauen, and the conſeque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t priuation of vnſpeakable ioyes; the moſt excellent whereof is, the fruition of the ſacred Trinitie <hi>in bliſſefull viſion.</hi> This paine is equall to all, <hi>Tempore et Gradu.</hi> In <hi>time,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is an <hi>eternall</hi> depriuation: In <hi>degree,</hi> becauſe it is a <hi>totall</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priuation, ioyned with infallible deſpayre.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The poſitiue payne (called <hi>Poena Senſus</hi>) is partly inward from an inward cauſe, and partly out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward from an outward cauſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Poena au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, &amp;c. <hi>Inuenal.</hi>
                  </note>The inward payne is the ſting of conſcience, the gnawing of that
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:16521:15"/> worme, which hath her life per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuated in our death.</p>
               <p>This payne is equall to all, in <hi>duration</hi> but not in <hi>degree,</hi> becauſe it is varied according to the guilt whence it doth proceed.</p>
               <p>The outward payn is affliction in the whole man, Body, &amp; Soule, by ſuch exquiſite inſtrumentall meanes as God decreeth in his wiſedome, &amp; executeth by his po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, to demonſtrate his Iuſtice.</p>
               <p>And if any man doubt, how that can be called an <hi>outward</hi> puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which is inflicted on the Soule, beeing an <hi>inward</hi> ſubſtance in her coniunction with the Body: <hi>I anſwer,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>The Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally are of opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that there is</hi> Fire (<hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly taken in hell:</hi> S. Aug. l. 21: de Ciuit. Dei: ca: 10 S. Hieron. ad Auitum <hi>S.</hi> Aug. vide. Zanch. de Ope. parte 1. lib. 4. cap 19. <hi>without all doubt there is outward meanes of ſenſible pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment.</hi>
                  </note> That the ſenſible puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Fire,</hi> is called outward, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is originally <hi>extra ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam,</hi> as the other ſenſible puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the <hi>worme</hi> is called inward becauſe it ſpringeth within the ſoule it ſelfe.</p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:16521:16"/>
               <p>Likewiſe the ſenſible puniſhment by <hi>Fire</hi> is outward, as it worketh on the body, being an outward ſubſtance: and inward as it work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth on the ſoule, which is an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſubſtance by her vnion with the body.</p>
               <p>And as the ſoule hath one ſtate in her ſelfe independe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, vpon her ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration from the body, and an other in the body vpon her reuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with it: ſo in the firſt, ſhe ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth outward payne immediately, and in the ſecond, ſhee ſuffereth outward paine immediatly, parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipating eternall torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, with the old companion of her momenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny pleaſure.</p>
               <p>And as the outward payne of <hi>Fire</hi> primarily inflicted on the body, doth worke effectually to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict the ſoule: ſo the inward payne of the <hi>worme</hi> ariſing, and dwelling within the ſoule, worketh effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:16521:16"/> to vex the body: That as they had mutuall offices in the tranſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory delight of their ſinnes, ſo they may haue mutuall offices in the horror of their exceſſiue pangs.</p>
               <p>In this outward paine two things are to be noted as before: <hi>Tempus &amp; Gradui.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In <hi>time</hi> this payne is equall to all men. And this is common in all the payns of hell, all being equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in eternity, becauſe in reſpect of duration, there is neither more nor leſſe in that with in <hi>Infinite.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hence is that wofull ſentence, <hi>Go ye curſed into euerlasting fire. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting,</hi> not <hi>temporarie,</hi> as <hi>Origen</hi> falſly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceiued, preiudicing Gods Iuſtice in extolling his mercy: both which are one in him, but differ in their effects towards vs.</p>
               <p>In <hi>degree,</hi> this payne is vnequall according to the inequality of ſin: God in his diſtributiue Iuſtice, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lotting
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:16521:17"/> ſeuerall portions of paine, according to the ſeuerall propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of ſinne.</p>
               <p>For though there be a proper deſigned place of Hell, and in it ſome common inſtrument of payne, yet God moſt prouidently ordereth the execution of his Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice.</p>
               <p>And though we are not directly led by expreſſe Scripture to affirm it confidently, yet we may ſuppoſe it very probably, that God eyther cohibiteth the actiue power of the <hi>inſtrument,</hi> or ſtrengtheneth the ability of the <hi>Patient,</hi> or both, to make a difference of payne.</p>
               <p>Howſoeuer, this is vnqueſtiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that for this purpoſe hee vſeth ſuch wiſe meanes as ſeeme beſt to his will; which being perpetually accompanied with ſingular equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, can purpoſe nothing vniuſtly: and being aſſiſted with illimited
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:16521:17"/> might, can enterpriſe nothing vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>effectually.</p>
               <p>Concerning all the paines, of what kind, number, or quality ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer they are, we muſt know (God grant we neuer feele) that there is neither caſe in them, nor releaſe from them. The pitifull vnpitied wretches ſuffer vnſufferably, in meaſure of time vnmeaſurable.</p>
               <p>THVS then we acknowledge, that ſinnes are <hi>veniall</hi> by grace, but <hi>mortall</hi> in their proper deſert: and that ſinnes are <hi>vnaequall</hi> many wayes, and that the puniſhment of all ſinnes is <hi>aequall</hi> in <hi>time,</hi> but <hi>vnaequall</hi> in <hi>degree.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now to obtayne abſolution <hi>à Culpa &amp; Poena,</hi> we muſt haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to Gods mercy, becauſe his Iuſtice doth puniſh vs conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering vs, as we are of our ſelues.</p>
               <p>And to find this mercy, we muſt
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:16521:18"/> haue recourſe to God, in Ieſus Chriſt our Lord, becauſe we are not worthy of it, for any thing in our ſelues. This is both <hi>pietie</hi> and <hi>ſafety.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Neither muſt we doe thus in <hi>profeſſion</hi> only,<note place="margin">Concil. Trid. Seſſ. 6. cap: 9:</note> as ſometimes the <hi>Papiſts</hi> doe, but in <hi>action</hi> alſo, as ſometimes they doe not, as it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth by their opinion before deliuered, and farther ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare in their doctrine enſuing.</p>
               <p>But firſt we obſerue, that as Chriſt only is <hi>via meriti,</hi> for which we are <hi>meritoriouſly</hi> pardoned, ſo there is required alſo <hi>via medij,</hi> by which we may <hi>actually</hi> receiue this pardon, becauſe the ſalue of his merits muſt be applied to the ſoares of our ſoules. For nothing can produce an effect in that which it doth not <hi>Contingere vel ſubſtantia, vel virtute ſaltem.</hi> As the Sun being in his ſubſtance placed
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:16521:18"/> ſo farre aboue, cannot produce any effect by working vpon infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour bodyes, but by a <hi>virtuall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tact.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Our Lord hath a double ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration: <hi>Extraordinary</hi> &amp; <hi>Immediate:</hi> or <hi>Ordinary</hi> and <hi>Mediate.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The firſt we are to beholde and admire, but we cannot ſafely rely on it. For we muſt herein remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber an old rule (applyable to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther purpoſes) <hi>Notandum ſi ſemel, vtendum vt ſaepè.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſecond therefore is that, whereunto wee now bend our eyes.</p>
               <p>To this end there are certayne <hi>Euangelicall</hi> meanes, with which Chriſt doth concur.</p>
               <p>They are ſuch, as are aſſigned by him.</p>
               <p>They are aſſigned by him, which expreſſely, or conſequently are contained in his word. For wee
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:16521:19"/> muſt eſtimate the things of God, according to a rule deliuered by him, either ſpeaking with his mouth, or dictating by his ſpirit.</p>
               <p>Hereupon we deſeruedly reiect that poſition of the Church of Rome,<note place="margin">Rhem. Teſt. annot. in Iob. <hi>13.10.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Veniall ſinnes may be remitted by holy water, and other ſacred Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies:</hi> which ſentence hath in it a double impiety and falſhood.</p>
               <p>The firſt in diminiſhing the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of our ſinnes, which are in their proper merit condignly pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhable by eternall death.</p>
               <p>The ſecond in extolling the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue of their ceremonies, which ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not haue in them ſo gratious a power.</p>
               <p>Neither is it enough to ſay, that theſe ceremonies, as <hi>holy water</hi> &amp; the like, worke not this effect <hi>vi ſua,</hi> but <hi>virtute Chriſti.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For as the power of remiſſion of
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:16521:19"/> ſinnes is only in God (a miniſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all office being in the Church by commiſſion from him) ſo the meanes which we muſt vſe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the remiſſion by, muſt be ſuch, as hee appointeth by his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed will.</p>
               <p>For as to diuide the firſt to any perſon from him, ſo to communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate the ſecond to any meanes not decreed by him, it is to euacuate the high price of our Redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and to trample vnder feet, the bleſſed couenant of happy peace. Neyther is it enough to ſay, that the Church deuiſeth not theſe things ſimply of her ſelfe, but that it is Chriſts promiſe to concurre with the Church by his infallible Spirit:</p>
               <p>For they muſt remember, that it is the duety of the Church to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur with him, according to infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble directions deliuered in his
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:16521:20"/> word.</p>
               <p>As for immediate reuelations, none but <hi>Enthuſiasts</hi> rely thereon. But we know that the <hi>Spirit</hi> doth rather <hi>aſpirare,</hi> then <hi>inſpirare</hi> in theſe dayes.</p>
               <p>Wherefore leauing vnwarranta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>aſperſions</hi> to ſuch <hi>Aquarij,</hi> as a <hi>nouell</hi> conceipte, proued one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by an ingenious deluſion: We acknowledge that <hi>Naturall</hi> bloud and <hi>water,</hi> iſſuing out of our Lords ſides, doe <hi>per viam meriti</hi> purchaſe the remiſſion of all our ſinnes: and that the <hi>ſacramentall</hi> bloud &amp; <hi>water</hi> in the holy myſteries figured ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, doe <hi>per viam medij,</hi> apply, ſeale, and confirme the ſame vnto vs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrumentally, by the effectuall operation of the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
               <p>He that diminiſheth the merit of Chriſts death, deſtroieth the hope of his owne life.</p>
               <p>I liue in him, who died for me.</p>
            </div>
            <closer>AMEN.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="author_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:16521:20"/>
            <head>The Author to the Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Ourteous Reader:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>If any faults haue eſcaped me, in penning this little diſcourſe (which I may be occaſioned hereafter to call <hi>Principium doloris mei</hi>) I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not expect, that thou ſhouldest eſteeme them <hi>venial,</hi> becauſe I haue left that plea, and gained a loſſe vnto my ſelfe.</p>
            <p>If I ſhould craue pardon for diuulging it, thou mighteſt iuſt he anſwer, <hi>VVhile it remained, appertained it not vnto thee? And after it was</hi> printed, <hi>was it not in thine owne power?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Though I coulde fullie remooue ſuch likelie imputations, yet the reaſon being priuate, which cauſed me to make this publike, (and <hi>Secreta mea mihi</hi>) I muſt depend vpon thy gentle interpretation. Onelie thus much I giue thee to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, that I rather ſought profit hereby to learne from others, then credit to teache anie.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:16521:21"/>
            <p>But if my ſucceſſe proue anſwerable to my honeſt deſire, thou ſhalt find in time, that my Tongue and Pen, are conſecrated to thy good. Farewell.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine in our Lord <hi>IESVS, Theophilus Pyggons.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="explanatory_textual_note">
            <pb facs="tcp:16521:21"/>
            <head>Pag. 3. lin. 18.</head>
            <p>Whereas it is ſayd, that <hi>the forme of ſinne is an obliquity in the ſubstance,</hi>
               <note place="margin">—dum breuis eſſe laboro Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcurus fio.</note> 
               <hi>or quality, or action of a reaſonable Creature,</hi> it is to be vnderſtood, that <hi>Malum ſubiectatur</hi> (as the Schoolemen ſpeake) the euill of ſinne, and the deformity (which is the form of it) hath its ſubſiſtence finally in a <hi>Subſtance,</hi> as being the laſt, and independent ſubiect ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. But it is immediately in the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and corrupt quality of the Agent.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="addendum">
            <pb facs="tcp:16521:22"/>
            <head>Pag. 20. this ſhould haue bin added as a Marginall note ouer againſt the fift line.</head>
            <p>If the laſt commandement (as wee eſteeme it) ſhould be diuided into two, <hi>propter diuerſitatem Obiecto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum:</hi> by the ſame reaſon it ſhould be no commandement at all, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the ſame <hi>things</hi> are forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den in the ſeuenth &amp; eighth com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements before. The diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence therefore of the <hi>manner</hi> of forbidding theſe things, diſtingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth the tenth commandement from the ſeuenth and eighth: But the difference of the <hi>matter</hi> in it, doth not make it diſtinguiſhed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to two ſeuerall precepts, as Papiſts affirme. But as our Lord epitomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zeth and reduceth ten comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements vnto two, ſo here all the particulars make but one. And as to make the firſt and ſecond com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements
<pb facs="tcp:16521:22"/> one, it is to ioyne things ſeparate, ſo to make this one commandement two, it is to ſeparate things conioyned. To do the firſt, it is to match together in ſeuerall Tribes, and to doe the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, it is to make a diuorce of parties lawfully married. The Author that made this confuſion, and diuiſion, is greater then his reaſon: for though <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> beganne it, yet his reaſon to make three commandements in the firſt Table <hi>propter Trinitatem,</hi> is a witty Analogy onely: and his reaſon to make ſeauen in the ſecond Table by diuiding the laſt, is of no ſolidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. <hi>Zanchius</hi> his ſeuere, but true cenſure, touching this particular, is worthy to be conſidered: <hi>Zanch. de Red. in Tractat. de Decalogo, Theſi tertia.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:16521:23"/>
            <head>Some principall errors in the <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, correct thus:</hi>
            </head>
            <p>Pag. 2. Lin. 12 For <hi>Perſons</hi> (as it is printed in ſome Copies, and is plaine <hi>Neſtoria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſme</hi>) read <hi>Perſon,</hi> in the Epiſtle to the Papiſts.</p>
            <p>Pag. 20. line 5. For theſe words, <hi>and the matter coueted be diuers,</hi> reade <hi>(though the matter coueted be diuers)</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Pag. 24. In the margent, theſe words, <hi>S. Auguſt.</hi> are ſuperfluous.</p>
            <p>Pag. 24. lin. 15. For <hi>immediatelie</hi> in the ſecond place, reade, <hi>mediatelie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Pag. 25. lin. 14. For <hi>within,</hi> reade, <hi>which is.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:16521:23"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
